<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39488504</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2754-6993</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Schizophrenia (Heidelberg, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Schizophrenia (Heidelb)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Efficacy of xanomeline and trospium chloride in schizophrenia: pooled results from three 5-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, EMERGENT trials.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>102</StartPage><MedlinePgn>102</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">102</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41537-024-00525-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In the 5-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled EMERGENT-1 (NCT03697252), EMERGENT-2 (NCT04659161), and EMERGENT-3 (NCT04738123) trials, xanomeline and trospium chloride (formerly known as KarXT) significantly improved symptoms of schizophrenia and was generally well tolerated. We pooled data from the EMERGENT trials to further characterize the efficacy of xanomeline/trospium and provide sufficient statistical power to analyze responses in participant subgroups. In pooled analyses, xanomeline/trospium significantly improved Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) total score at week 5 versus placebo (least squares mean difference, -9.9; 95% confidence interval, -12.4, -7.3; p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.0001; Cohen's d effect size, 0.65). PANSS subscale and Clinical Global Impression-Severity scores also improved significantly with xanomeline/trospium versus placebo. Subgroup analyses consistently favored xanomeline/trospium over placebo regardless of differences in participant age, sex, race, body mass index, and baseline PANSS total score. These results add to existing evidence demonstrating robust and reliable improvements in symptoms with xanomeline/trospium across a broad spectrum of people with schizophrenia.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaul</LastName><ForeName>Inder</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bristol Myers Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sawchak</LastName><ForeName>Sharon</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bristol Myers Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Claxton</LastName><ForeName>Amy</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bristol Myers Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sauder</LastName><ForeName>Colin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bristol Myers Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hassman</LastName><ForeName>Howard H</ForeName><Initials>HH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CenExel-Hassman Research Institute, Marlton, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kakar</LastName><ForeName>Rishi</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Segal Trials, Lauderhill, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walling</LastName><ForeName>David P</ForeName><Initials>DP</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8638-2086</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CenExel-Collaborative Neuroscience Research, Los Alamitos, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Citrome</LastName><ForeName>Leslie</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6098-9266</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>New York Medical College, Valhalla, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Haiyuan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-0903-9349</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bristol Myers Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miller</LastName><ForeName>Andrew C</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bristol Myers Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brannan</LastName><ForeName>Stephen K</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0922-5970</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bristol Myers Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA. sbrannan@karunatx.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Schizophrenia (Heidelb)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918367987006676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2754-6993</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="ErratumIn"><RefSource>Schizophrenia (Heidelb). 2025 Mar 18;11(1):44. doi: 10.1038/s41537-025-00595-0.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">40102406</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><CoiStatement>I.K., S.S., A.C., C.S., and H.Z. are employees of Karuna Therapeutics, a Bristol Myers Squibb company. A.C.M and S.K.B. are consultants of Karuna Therapeutics, a Bristol Myers Squibb company. H.H.H. was a principal investigator for the EMERGENT-1 and EMERGENT-2 trials. R.K. was a principal investigator for the EMERGENT-2 trial. L.C. is a consultant for AbbVie/Allergan, Acadia, Adamas, Alkermes, Angelini, Astellas, Avanir, Axsome, Biogen, BioXcel, Boehringer Ingelheim, Cadent Therapeutics, Cerevel, Clinilabs, COMPASS, Delpor, Eisai, Enteris BioPharma, HLS Therapeutics, Idorsia, INmune Bio, Impel, Intra-Cellular Therapies, Janssen, Karuna, Lundbeck, Luye, Lyndra, MapLight, Marvin, Medavante-ProPhase, Merck, Mitsubishi-Tanabe Pharma, Neumora, Neurocrine, Neurelis, Noema, Novartis, Noven, Otsuka, Ovid, Praxis, Recordati, Relmada, Reviva, Sage, Sumitomo/Sunovion, Supernus, Teva, University of Arizona, Vanda, Wells Fargo, and one-off ad hoc consulting for individuals/entities conducting marketing, commercial, or scientific scoping research; is a speaker for AbbVie/Allergan, Acadia, Alkermes, Angelini, Axsome, BioXcel, Eisai, Idorsia, Intra-Cellular Therapies, Janssen, Lundbeck, Neurocrine, Noven, Otsuka, Recordati, Sage, Sunovion, Takeda, Teva, and CME activities organized by medical education companies such as Medscape, NACCME, NEI, Vindico, and universities and professional organizations/societies; owns stocks (small number of shares of common stock) in Bristol-Myers Squibb, Eli Lilly, J &amp; J, Merck, and Pfizer purchased &gt;10 years ago, and stock options: Reviva; receives royalties/publishing income from Taylor &amp; Francis (Editor-in-Chief, <i>Current Medical Research and Opinion</i>, 2022-date), Wiley (Editor-in-Chief, <i>International Journal of Clinical Practice</i>, through end 2019), UpToDate (reviewer), Springer Healthcare (book), Elsevier (Topic Editor, <i>Psychiatry, Clinical Therapeutics</i>). D.P.W. has received research support from AbbVie, Acadia, Alkermes, Allergan, Avanir, BMS, Cerevel, Indivior, IntraCellular, J &amp; J RPD, Karuna, Lupin, Lundbeck, Neurocrine, Novartis, Noven, Pfizer, Roche, Sage, Sunovion, and Takeda; and has received research support and served as a consultant for Biogen, Boehringer Ingelheim, Janssen, Lyndra, and Otsuka.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39488504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11531488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41537-024-00525-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41537-024-00525-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Paul, S. M., Yohn, S. E., Popiolek, M., Miller, A. C. &amp; Felder, C. C. Muscarinic acetylcholine receptor agonists as novel treatments for schizophrenia. <i>Am. J. Psychiatry</i><b>179</b>, 611&#x2013;627 (2022).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.21101083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35758639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shekhar, A. et al. Selective muscarinic receptor agonist xanomeline as a novel treatment approach for schizophrenia. <i>Am. J. Psychiatry</i><b>165</b>, 1033&#x2013;1039 (2008).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2008.06091591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18593778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bodick, N. C. et al. Effects of xanomeline, a selective muscarinic receptor agonist, on cognitive function and behavioral symptoms in Alzheimer disease. <i>Arch. Neurol.</i><b>54</b>, 465&#x2013;473 (1997).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archneur.1997.00550160091022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9109749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Indevus Pharmaceuticals. Sanctura (trospium chloride). Prescribing Information. 2012. Accessed 29 January 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breier, A., Brannan, S. K., Paul, S. M. &amp; Miller, A. C. Evidence of trospium&#x2019;s ability to mitigate cholinergic adverse events related to xanomeline: phase 1 study results. <i>Psychopharmacol. (Berl.)</i><b>240</b>, 1191&#x2013;1198 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00213-023-06362-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10102054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37036495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brannan, S. K. et al. Muscarinic cholinergic receptor agonist and peripheral antagonist for schizophrenia. <i>N. Engl. J. Med.</i><b>384</b>, 717&#x2013;726 (2021).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2017015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7610870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33626254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaul, I. et al. Efficacy and safety of the muscarinic receptor agonist KarXT (xanomeline-trospium) in schizophrenia (EMERGENT-2) in the USA: results from a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, flexible-dose phase 3 trial. <i>Lancet</i><b>403</b>, 160&#x2013;170 (2024).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)02190-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38104575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaul, I. et al. Efficacy and safety of xanomeline-trospium chloride in schizophrenia: a randomized clinical trial. <i>JAMA Psychiatry</i><b>81</b>, 749&#x2013;756 (2024).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2024.0785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11063924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38691387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brannan, S. K. et al. Safety and efficacy of KarXT in patients with schizophrenia in the randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled EMERGENT trials. Presented at: American Society of Clinical Pscyhopharmacology; Miami, FL; 30 May&#x2013;2 June 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brannan, S. K. et al. Categorical response rates, time course of response, and symptom domains of response with KarXT (xanomeline&#x2013;trospium) in the EMERGENT-3 trial. Presented at: European College of Neuropsychopharmacology; Barcelona, Spain; 7&#x2013;10 October 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Correll, C. U. Unleashing the power of pooled and subgroup analyses in psychiatry. <i>Int. Clin. Psychopharmacol.</i><b>37</b>, 223&#x2013;224 (2022).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/YIC.0000000000000423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35833286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kane, J. M. et al. Safety and tolerability of lumateperone for the treatment of schizophrenia: a pooled analysis of late-phase placebo- and active-controlled clinical trials. <i>Int. Clin. Psychopharmacol.</i><b>36</b>, 244&#x2013;250 (2021).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/YIC.0000000000000371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8322041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34054112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasrallah, H. A. et al. The safety and tolerability of cariprazine in long-term treatment of schizophrenia: a post hoc pooled analysis. <i>BMC Psychiatry</i><b>17</b>, 305 (2017).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12888-017-1459-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5571492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28836957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Earley, W. et al. Efficacy of cariprazine on negative symptoms in patients with acute schizophrenia: a post hoc analysis of pooled data. <i>Schizophr. Res.</i><b>204</b>, 282&#x2013;288 (2019).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2018.08.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30172595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kay, S. R., Fiszbein, A. &amp; Opler, L. A. The positive and negative syndrome scale (PANSS) for schizophrenia. <i>Schizophr. Bull.</i><b>13</b>, 261&#x2013;276 (1987).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/schbul/13.2.261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3616518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leucht, S. Measurements of response, remission, and recovery in schizophrenia and examples for their clinical application. <i>J. Clin. Psychiatry</i><b>75</b>, 11378 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.13049su1c.02</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24581453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leucht, S. et al. Linking PANSS negative symptom scores with the Clinical Global Impressions Scale: understanding negative symptom scores in schizophrenia. <i>Neuropsychopharmacology</i><b>44</b>, 1589&#x2013;1596 (2019).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41386-019-0363-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6785000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30836381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marder, S. R., Davis, J. M. &amp; Chouinard, G. The effects of risperidone on the five dimensions of schizophrenia derived by factor analysis: combined results of the North American trials. <i>J. Clin. Psychiatry</i><b>58</b>, 538&#x2013;546 (1997).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.v58n1205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9448657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haro, J. M. et al. The Clinical Global Impression-Schizophrenia scale: a simple instrument to measure the diversity of symptoms present in schizophrenia. <i>Acta Psychiatr. Scand. Suppl.</i><b>107</b>, 16&#x2013;23 (2003).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0447.107.s416.5.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12755850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leucht, S. et al. What does the PANSS mean? <i>Schizophr. Res.</i><b>79</b>, 231&#x2013;238 (2005).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2005.04.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15982856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cutler, A. J., Matthews, D. M. A focused approach: targeting muscarinic receptors in schizophrenia. Presented at: 29th Annual National Psychopharmacology Update of the Nevada Psychiatric Association; Las Vegas, NV; 14&#x2013;17 February, (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Correll, C. U., Angelov, A. S., Miller, A. C., Weiden, P. J. &amp; Brannan, S. K. Safety and tolerability of KarXT (xanomeline-trospium) in a phase 2, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study in patients with schizophrenia. <i>Schizophrenia</i><b>8</b>, 109 (2022).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41537-022-00320-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9719488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36463237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sauder, C. et al. Effectiveness of KarXT (xanomeline-trospium) for cognitive impairment in schizophrenia: post hoc analyses from a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase 2 study. <i>Transl. Psychiatry</i><b>12</b>, 491 (2022).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41398-022-02254-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9681874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36414626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiden, P. J. et al. Antipsychotic efficacy of KarXT (xanomeline-trospium): post hoc analysis of positive and negative syndrome scale categorical response rates, time course of response, and symptom domains of response in a phase 2 study. <i>J Clin Psychiatry</i><b>83</b>, 21m14316 (2022).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.21m14316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35552528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durgam, S. et al. Global improvement with cariprazine in the treatment of bipolar I disorder and schizophrenia: a pooled post hoc analysis. <i>Int J. Clin. Pr.</i><b>71</b>, e13037 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijcp.13037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5765496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29119668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel, M. et al. Efficacy of cariprazine in bipolar I depression across patient characteristics: a post hoc analysis of pooled randomized, placebo-controlled studies. <i>Int Clin. Psychopharmacol.</i><b>36</b>, 76&#x2013;83 (2021).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/YIC.0000000000000344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7846289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33230026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huhn, M. et al. Comparative efficacy and tolerability of 32 oral antipsychotics for the acute treatment of adults with multi-episode schizophrenia: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. <i>Lancet</i><b>394</b>, 939&#x2013;951 (2019).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31135-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6891890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31303314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horan, W. P. et al. Potential impact of KarXT on negative symptoms in acute schizophrenia: an analysis of pooled data from 3 trials. Presented at: CNS Summit; Boston, MA; 8&#x2013;11 November 2023, Poster 43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barabassy, A. et al. Safety and tolerability of cariprazine in patients with schizophrenia: a pooled analysis of eight phase II/III studies. <i>Neuropsychiatr. Dis. Treat.</i><b>17</b>, 957&#x2013;970 (2021).
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/NDT.S301225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8040316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33854317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>